Guide to the Greater Kansas City Council on Religion and Race Collection
University of Kansas
Greater Kansas City Council on Religion and Race records
1960-1993
University of Kansas Kenneth Spencer Research Library Kansas Collection 1450 Poplar Lane, Lawrence, KS 66045-7616 Phone: (785)864-4334 Fax: (785)864-5803 URL: http://spencer.lib.ku.edu
Greater Kansas City Council on Religion and Race
16.5 linear ft (17 boxes), 1 oversize box, 3 oversize folders
This collection of the records of the Greater Kansas City Council on Religion and Race includes administrative records of the organization and collected information on issues of interest, particularly fair housing and education.
RH MS 786
RH MS 1217
RH MS Q274
RH MS R232
Restrictions on Access
None
Acquisition Information
Gift, Ruth G. Shecter, 1977, 2004
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
- RH MS 786
- A/C's Bank Records through 1973 (Box Box 1:)
  - Bank Statements, 1967-1972 (Folder 1)
  - Proposal for Refunding of Housing Relocation Assistance Project, 1970 (Folder 2)
  - CRR Blank Applications (Folder 3)
  - Douglass State Bank, 1969-1970 (Folder 4)
  - Cancelled Checks (Folder 5)
  - Swope Parkway National Bank (Folder 6)
  - Board Members, 1970 (Folder 7)
  - Bibliography and Reports, 1970-1974 (Folder 8)
  - Council Proposal and Reports, 1970-1971 (Folder 9)
  - Douglass State Bank Statements (Folder 10)
  - Board Meeting, 1972 (Folder 11)
  - Vouchers, 1970 (Folder 12)
  - The Ford Foundation, 1970 (Folder 13)
  - Requisition: Supplies and Equipment Purchased (Folder 14)
  - Insurance, 1969-1971 (Folder 15)
  - Prentice-Hall, 1971 (Folder 16)
  - Pitney-Bowes: Postage Meter (Folder 17)
  - Request for Judicatory Funding, 1970 (Folder 18)
  - Southwestern Bell - Paid Phone Bills (Folder 19)
  - Douglass State Bank, 1972 (Folder 20)
  - Progress Association for Economic Development (Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Accounts Receivable (Folder 22)
  - Project Equality, 1970-1971 (Folder 23)
  - Moss Printing, Co. (Folder 24)
  - Paper Supply Co. (Folder 25)
  - JS Publications (Folder 26)
  - The Call (Folder 27)
  - Mid-West Duplicators, Inc (Folder 28)
  - Vouchers - Blank (Folder 29)
  - Loan Application - Douglass State Bank (Folder 30)
  - Kansas City Star (Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous Accounts (Folder 32)
  - IBM, 1973 (Folder 33)
  - Bank Checks (Folder 34-35)
  - Tempo Company (Scriptomatic) (Folder 36)
  - Tiffany's Attic Benefit, 1972 (Folder 37)
  - Board Packet: Reports, Statement, etc. (Folder 38)
- Miscellaneous Annual Board Meetings and MTG Materials (Box Box 2:)
  - Membership and other Information (Folder 1)
  - Board Memos, 1970-1971 (Folder 2)
  - Membership Committee, 1968-1969 (Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Board of Directors papers, 1970-1971 (Folder 4-5)
  - Board of Directors Meeting MInutes, 1969 (Folder 6)
  - Kansas City Clergy List (Folder 7)
  - Directories (except Postal) (Folder 8)
  - Labels - Carbon (Folder 9)
  - West Oakland Switchboard - Legal Aid Organization (Folder 10)
  - Project Circle: A Study for Proposal of a Universal Crisis Phone Information Center, 1970 (Folder 11)
  - Annual Meeting Information, 1966 (Folder 12)
  - By-Laws (Folder 13)
  - Funding, 1968-1969 (Folder 14)
  - Finances, 1968-1969 (Folder 15)
  - Board of Directors, 1969 (Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Accounts (Folder 17)
  - Executive Committee Meeting (Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee (Folder 19)
  - Board Membership and Committee Appointments (Folder 20)
  - Meeting Minutes and Memos, etc., 1965-1970 (Folder 21-22)
  - Programs (Folder 23)
  - Fellowship Committee (Folder 24)
  - American Lutheran Crisis Fund (Folder 25)
- (Box Box 3)
  - Packet sent to board of directors (7.21.71); packet given to board, and sent to board (12.15.70); November financial statement, staff brochure, etc. (Folder 1)
  - Finance committee; mental health association (Kansas City); Baytown; general correspondence; housing statement of welcome (Folder 2)
  - Housing committee; steering committee; Hickman Mills Ruskin Heights; employment committee (Folder 3)
  - Inquiries (general housing); government committee; fair housing pledges; CIA of KCK (Folder 4)
  - Publicity; housing referendum; veterans administration; clergymen who have signed pledge; letters to school boards and mayors (Folder 5)
  - Statements and sermons (Folder 6)
  - Wyandotte; Excelsior Springs; press releases - H.K.; East (Folder 7)
  - Southwest; country club area (Folder 8)
  - North East; Olathe; Westport; Liberty; fair housing councils in other cities (letters) (Folder 9)
  - Working committee; Lee's Summit; letters of endorsement; associate sponsors (Folder 10)
  - Good neighbor pledge; Blue Springs; national sponsors; letter from businessmen in regard to pledge campaign (Folder 11)
  - Business men and women who have signed pledge; rally; youth committee; housing-home strategy committee (Folder 12)
  - List of judicatories (12.17.71); judicatory contributions; Harmony Homes, Inc.; housing conference (Folder 13)
  - Grandview Belton; loose material; housing - the rally; clergy convocation (Folder 14)
  - Public information committee; board meeting minutes (1971) (Folder 15)
- Some program G.N. proposal; Pledge - MBR. lists; News rel. - speakers; Bureau - some board material (Box Box 4:)
  - Judicatory correspondence; members and judicatory contribution (1970) (Folder 1)
  - Membership list; renewal letter forms; new membership letter forms (Folder 2)
  - Membership drive letters and membership renewal applications; membership correspondence (1970) (Folder 3)
  - Newsletters (Folder 4)
  - Housing committee (Folder 5)
  - Press releases (Folder 6)
  - Newspaper media serving greater Kansas City; proposal to art craft corporation; American Lutheran crisis fund grant (Folder 7)
  - Church women united, proposal (1971); circle (1970-71); operation greenway (Folder 8)
  - Dinners for Ten; film preview; speaker's kit (Folder 9)
  - Vouchers (1970); bylaws; statement of purpose (Folder 10)
  - Annual meeting (6.29.71); board meeting minutes (July, 1970) (Folder 11)
  - Board material (4.19.71); news clippings; citation award dinner (Folder 12)
  - Arrangements committee annual meeting (1968); newspaper clippings (Folder 13)
  - Fellowship house; housing northern Virginia (Folder 14)
  - National conference on religion and race; memo - national council of churches; NAACP; national institute on religion and race; greater St. Louis committee for freedom of residence; hate file! (Folder 15)
- Genlins and bank records, 1965- (Box Box 5:)
  - Legis - mental health (Folder 1)
  - Legis - Medicare; legis - medic are (1965) (Folder 2)
  - Project equality; new releases (Folder 3)
  - Office relocation; personnel (Folder 4)
  - Job applications; news - CCR mailing (Folder 5)
  - Legis - migratory waterfowl -- S.922 (commerce committee) (Folder 6)
  - Copies - news; small business administrative committee (Folder 7)
  - Education; speaker's file; religion and race conference (Folder 8)
  - Ecumenical library; community organizations; Presbytery office (Folder 9)
  - Contributions (1965-67) (Folder 10)
  - United Presbyterian; savin business machines (Folder 11)
  - Dorothy Dean; Lorraine Reese; minutes (Folder 12)
  - Rap; legis - medic are (1965) (Folder 13)
  - Education file; bulletins (Folder 14)
  - Finance committee (Folder 15)
  - Finance committee - part 2 (Folder 16)
- Financial and administrative files (Box Box 6:)
  - Paid bills - Douglas bank (1967) (Folder 1)
  - Funding requested; finances; Todd Pavela fund (Folder 2)
  - Financial reports; bank correspondence; January, 1969 (Folder 3)
  - Vouchers, February - May (1969) (Folder 4)
  - Vouchers, Jun - Aug, Oct - Dec (1969) (Folder 5)
  - Disbursements, except for payroll (1969); paid bills (1969); first quarter vouchers (1968) (Folder 6)
  - Vouchers - second quarter - April and May (1968) (Folder 7)
  - Vouchers, Jun - Sep (1968) (Folder 8)
  - Vouchers, Oct - Dec (1968) (Folder 9)
  - Payroll tax reports (1968); payment due - stamp = brochure; bank statements (1966 and prior) (Folder 10)
  - Second quarter budget and anticipated receipts (1968); bank deposit slips (1967-69) (Folder 11)
  - Paid bills - Douglas bank (1966 and prior) (Folder 12)
  - Salaries record - City national bank (Folder 13)
  - Project equality - vouchers; financial sponsorship (Folder 14)
  - Kansas City earning tax; mo. withholding tax; taxfile - instructions (Folder 15)
  - Equipment: inventory, insurance, information about; Pitney-Bowes, Inc. (1968) (Folder 16)
  - Office equipment (1968); bulk mailing (Folder 17)
  - Financial file, miscellaneous (1968); bank statements (1968) (Folder 18)
  - Federal W.I and F.I.C.A.; cancelled checks (1968) (Folder 19)
  - Financial reports; bank statements - city material (1967) (Folder 20)
- Administration and financial education (Box Box 7:)
  - Formation of textbook committee; follow-up on Mid-America conference on education (Folder 1)
  - School segregation articles; middle school ad hoc committee for quality integrated education (Folder 2)
  - Analysis of trends in, and demand and marketability for, residential and nonresidential land in the greater Kansas City area, and designated renewal priority areas of Kansas City, Missouri (Folder 3)
  - Endorsements - education conference; that attitude of African American high school students in Kansas City, Missouri (Folder 4)
  - Equality of educational opportunity booklet; education committee (2 copies); education committee (1968-69) (Folder 5)
  - Bond - education; education committee - minutes and correspondence (chronological) (Folder 6)
  - Kansas City, Missouri education affairs (1968-69); education file - Keith Berry (Folder 7)
  - Educational resources; colleges and universities (Folder 8)
  - Kansas City, Missouri board of education; education in the urban crisis; desegregated schools (Folder 9)
  - Education - general file (Folder 10)
  - Midwest research institute; education papers from Dan Levine (Folder 11)
  - Education - Kansas City, Missouri (Folder 12)
  - Education - Kansas City and Missouri - discrimination (Folder 13)
  - Education committee (Folder 14)
  - Education pamphlets (Folder 15)
  - Analysis of trends in, and demand and marketability for, residential and non-residential land in the greater Kansas City area, and in designated renewal priority areas of Kansas City, Missouri - booklet (Folder 16)
  - M.A.O.P. and Westside; a descent home for all; Kentucky and Chicago (Folder 17)
- Education and employment communications (Box Box 8:)
  - A.F.L. - C.I.O.; C.O.R.E.; NAACP; Federationist; Indian enterprises, inc. (Folder 1)
  - Presbytery of Detroit; employment and economic development (Folder 2)
  - Press releases; middle school; general employment; Middle America ethnic power (February, 1971) (Folder 3)
  - Annual report of Kansas City, Missouri public schools; employment and economic development committee (Folder 4)
  - EEO commission (Folder 5)
  - Economic development (2 copies); employment (Folder 6)
  - Employment and economic development committee (1968-69); employment committee; Western electric (Folder 7)
  - Right extremists; newsletter; regional health and welfare council; reports; religious statements on racial future (Folder 8)
  - St. Louis conference on religion and race (Paul Hanlon); southern regional council; urban league; southern work (Folder 9)
  - Washington University; Missouri commission on human rights (Peter Robertson); welfare rights - poverty issues (Folder 10)
  - Poverty; police - community relations (2 copies); employment (Folder 11)
  - Memo; literature backorder; Reeb memorial service (Folder 12)
  - 1000 member club; funds received (before 1970) (Folder 13)
  - Violence; press releases; list of addresses; general A-Z; police and community relations (Folder 14)
  - Missouri coordinating council on rights; discrimination in private clubs (Folder 15)
  - Public accommodations; LEAP; Ed and Ec correspondence (outgoing); CEP; economic development (Folder 16)
  - Tri-Faith employment project; employment general file (Folder 17)
  - Traveling reading seminar [Bennik, Doll, Perroni, Steering committee] (goal date, 4.14.71) (Folder 18)
  - Education conference (Folder 19)
- Community relations and R.A.P. (Box Box 9:)
  - Racial organizations; white racism - suburban action programs; regional health and welfare; P.I.C.; friends of C.U.A. (Folder 1)
  - C.U.A.; coordinating council; freedom of residence; Missouri commission on human rights; M.I.C.A.; miscellaneous memoranda, etc. (Folder 2)
  - Commission on human relations - Mrs. Maurice E. Culver; human relations news; housing conference (Folder 3)
  - Information service; homefront; inter-racial news service (Folder 4)
  - Delta ministry; H.O.M.E.; funding commitments (1969); membership committee (Folder 5)
  - Finances reports; housing referendum (Folder 6)
  - H.O.M.E. committee; defense department housing; fair housing (Folder 7)
  - Board meeting minutes, communication; finance committee; financial letters membership (Folder 8)
  - Funding requests; national legislation; leadership conference on civil rights; civilian review board (Folder 9)
  - R.A.P. general ledger and cash receipts (Folder 10)
  - Loose papers; closed data sheets; salary and wages payroll (Folder 11)
  - Loose papers - contribution lists; Swope Parkway National Bank (Folder 12)
  - R.A.P. referrals - data sheets (copies from L. Wilson, July, 1970, and Sep-Oct, 1970); members of committees concerning H-Rap and CRR (Folder 13)
  - RAP advisory committee; questionnaire forms; correspondence (Folder 14)
  - Concentrated employment program; community manual; fiscal year, 1970 (Folder 15)
  - CEP and RAP letter of understanding; national alliance of businessmen (Folder 16)
  - UMKC Win enrollee project - advisory council; community social support group, monthly report; RAP - Lee Summit, Missouri - CSSG (Folder 17)
  - Shawnee Mission housing council; proposals and contracts/Wilson's copy; contract and proposal (Folder 18)
  - CRR - RAP revised budget (10.5.70); request for modification and an 18 month extension; contract; RAP - contract - housing relocation project contracts (Folder 19)
  - Housing - Jim Zarda development company; transportation monthly - report; RAP request for client transportation (3.18.70); addendum to the request for client transportation (3.24.70) (Folder 20)
  - Travel information - critique of progress; data sheet; correspondence; RAP contract modification; requested data, 8.1.70 and 8.14.70 (Folder 21)
  - Correspondence; tax-cab rates (metropolitan area); RAP filing system (Folder 22)
  - Filing system; RAP committee - meetings, planning a workshop aimed at refunding (Jan-Feb, 1971); Pathfinder definition; housing - RAP advisory committee, minutes and memos; RAP correspondence; ongoing funding for RAP (Folder 23)
- R.A.P. continued (Box Box 10:)
  - Data sheets; correspondence (Folder 1)
  - RAP - community information blank forms; blank volunteer forms; 4 page presentation and CRR statement of purpose; blank interview forms (Folder 2)
  - Relocation assistance project journal accounting procedure; accounting - US department of labor contract; RAP - accounts payable; accounts paid (receipts) (Folder 3)
  - Advance payment; US department of labor - billing and bonding instructions; RAP invoices; sub-contract; invoices and statement of costs - finances (Folder 4)
  - RAP - notes - housing relocation project; organizations working with RAP; housing presentation (Folder 5)
  - H-RAP seminar (12.17.69) (Folder 6)
  - RAP - housing relocation committee; housing relocation project evaluation (Nov, 1969); housing monthly reports (Folder 7)
  - Housing monthly report (available real estate/rental financing); institute for community studies; administration monthly report (Folder 8)
  - Applicants; coordinator's correspondence; director's outgoing letters and memos (Folder 9)
  - Rev. James L. Blair; recommendations regarding assignment of VISTA volunteers to CRR; Frederick Kramer; client identification monthly report (Folder 10)
  - RAP referrals (from L. Wilson, July 1970)- data sheets (for follow-up screening)- Missouri state employment service; RAP referrals data sheet Missouri state employment (Folder 11)
  - RAP - interview data on clients (Folder 12)
  - C-RAP - possible RAP clients (Folder 13)
  - Institute for community studies (sub-contract); progress reports, travel and other expenses (Folder 14)
  - RAP; MAPS; RAP (9..70) (Folder 15)
  - RAP - supplies and equipment; VISTA; short summary of RAP; RAP staff meeting minutes (Folder 16)
  - RAP news releases; RAP job description - counselor interview; RAP job descriptions (Folder 17)
  - General service administration, federal supply service requisition; US labor department correspondence (outgoing) and (incoming) (Folder 18)
  - L.C. Wilson - daily diary (Folder 19)
  - Lawrence C. Wilson (incoming correspondence); RAP - available housing; housing (Folder 20)
- (Box Box 11)
  - Christ Episcopal (5.18.69); Knox Presbyterian (5.11.69) (Folder 1)
  - Cure d'Ars (5.11.69); Indian Heights (5.18.69) (Folder 2)
  - Regrets and cancellations (1969); evaluation sheets - tour (1969) (Folder 3)
  - Spring tour committee - miscellaneous (1969); SMHC spring homes tour (1970) (Folder 4)
  - Spring homes tour (1971); follow-ups, mailing, publicity, minority contacts, telephone, tour coordinator (Folder 5)
  - Prairie Village - Leawood (Folder 6)
  - Spring homes tour (1971); assignments, miscellaneous (Folder 7)
  - Evaluation sheets, special assignments, lists; business contact (public relation) (Folder 8)
  - Releases and materials sent out, mailing and publicity (1969) (Folder 9)
  - Tour coordinator, telephone, home listings, Spring homes tour (1969) (Folder 10)
  - Redeemer [and other churches, 1971) (Folder 11)
  - Civil rights act and fair housing (Folder 12)
  - Illinois, Nation of Immigrants, Temple of Bethel (Folder 13)
  - Fair housing; correspondence, Kansas City, Missouri, articles (Folder 14)
  - Northland, 1970 (Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1960-65 (Folder 16)
  - Shawnee - Merriam (Folder 17)
  - Johnson County H.R. commission (Folder 18)
  - Spring Homes Tour (1971); file copies, hospitality lists, miscellaneous, Hocker Grove junior high school (Folder 19)
- (Box Box 12)
  - Kansas City housing laws; Shawnee Mission housing council (Folder 1)
  - Harry Golden on anti-semitism; "Negro education...for what?"; New York in photographs (Folder 2)
  - Council's report and recommendations to the conference; White House conference "To fulfill these rights" (June, 1966) (Folder 3)
  - [Parvin] Shawmet (Folder 4)
  - SMHC miscellaneous and "Attitudes of Negro High school students..." (Folder 5)
  - Freedom fair [part one] (Folder 6)
  - Freedom fair [part two] (Folder 7)
  - Financial account information; metropolitan communications and media academy (Folder 8)
  - Financial reports (1969-71) (Folder 9)
  - Payroll reports - taxes (1969); Missouri department of labor; Missouri income tax reports; Kansas City earnings tax (Folder 10)
  - FICA (Folder 11)
  - Bank records - financial statements (and bylaws) (Folder 12)
  - Financial statements (Folder 13)
  - Master file (Folder 14)
  - Addresses and miscellaneous (Folder 15)
  - Housing relocation - job employment; proposal - department of labor (Folder 16)
  - Corporate registration (Folder 17)
  - Federal tax exempt records (Folder 18)
  - Contact file (Folder 19)
  - Volunteers, miscellaneous, volunteering (Folder 20)
  - "Corporate records" (Folder Book:)
- (Box Box 13)
  - Regional conference of community leaders on equal employment opportunity (Folder 1)
  - Manor South (Folder 2)
  - Tax status (1977) (Folder 3)
  - S-M housing council; miscellaneous, SMHC - stationary (Folder 4)
  - SMHC newsletters (Folder 5)
  - S-M housing council; SMHC board minutes (1975); SMHC minutes (1973-74) (Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous; insurance claims, suits, tenant complaints; miscellaneous (Folder 7)
  - Shawnee Mission housing council (Folder 8)
  - Building specifications for Parvin estates (Folder 9)
  - Pamphlets (Folder 10)
  - Booklets; equal opportunity in housing, "Privacy" and prejudice (Folder 11)
  - Booklets - "Discrimination costs" through "Pageant", et al. (Folder 12)
  - "Freedom budget" for all Americans - prejudice in children (Folder 13)
  - Race prejudice as self-rejection (Folder 14)
  - A time to heal - burning of African American churches (Folder 15)
  - "Race and Property", "Report of the National Advisory Commission on Civil Disorders", "Missouri Roster", "Kansas City's Hispanic Business Directory", "Crisis and Opportunity: Race Relations in Selma" (Folder Books:)
- (Box Box 14)
  - "Civil Rights and the American Negro", "Employer Assisted Housing", "Racial Isolation in the Public Schools", "Fair Housing Comes of Age", "Women Workers: Trends and Issues", "Housing Mobility: Promise of Illusion?", "Rental Housing Assistance - The Worsening Crisis", "Housing Our Families", "Our Housing Mess...and what can be done about it", "A Sheltered Crisis: The State of Fair Housing in the Eighties", "The State of the Cities, 1999", "New Initiatives in Fair Housing", "Measuring Racial Discrimination in American Housing Markets", "Displacement: How to Fight It" (Folder Books:)
  - Publications on fair housing (Folder 1)
  - Publications on fair housing (Folder 2)
  - Publications on fair housing and civil rights (Folder 3)
  - Fair housing and civil rights (Folder 4)
- (Box Box 15)
  - Publications on fair housing and civil rights (Folder 1)
  - Publications on fair housing and civil rights (Folder 2)
  - Fair housing and advertising (Folder 3)
  - Fair housing, diversity, hate crimes (Folder 4)
  - Fair housing, equal opportunity (Folder 5)
  - Fair housing (Folder 6)
  - Counseling minority group youth; "Hiring Negro Workers", fair housing handbook (Folder 7)
  - Prejudice and society; "Nicodemus: Negro Haven on the Solomon", citizen action for housing and renewal (Folder 8)
  - How the federal government builds ghettos; impact of housing patterns on job opportunities; miscellaneous (Folder 9)
  - Supreme Court, prejudiced, treatment of religion..., memorandum of law... (Folder 10)
  - "On recognizing the human species" through "The churches and the public" (Folder 11)
  - "Anti-Semitism in perspective" through Daedalus (Folder 12)
  - Special fund (Folder 13)
  - Financial documents (Folder 14)
  - Kansas advisory council on civil rights, receipts - statements, etc. (Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, mailing lists (Folder 16)
- (Box Box 16)
  - Addresses and City and State civil rights laws (Folder 1)
  - Police - community relations correspondence (Folder 2)
  - Conference planning (Folder 3)
  - Police - community relations (Folder 4)
  - Police - community relations in St. Louis (Folder 5)
  - Kansas (Folder 6)
  - Public inquiry by Kansas advisory committee on CCR (Folder 7)
  - Index cards, miscellaneous presentations (Folder 8)
  - Fair housing and equal rights (Folder 9)
  - Fair housing and equal rights (Folder 10)
  - Periodicals, neighbor, etc. (Folder 11)
- RH MS 1217
- (Box Box 1)
  - By-laws (Folder 1)
  - Statement of purpose (Folder 2)
  - Staff brochure (Folder 3)
  - Riots: Preparation, Programs and Response, 1968 (Folder 4)
  - Relocation Assistance Project: Policy and Procedure, 1970 June (Folder 5)
  - Annual meeting, 1970 (Folder 6)
  - Annual meeting, 1973 (Folder 7)
  - Staff meeting minutes, 1970 November 16 (Folder 8)
  - Board meeting minutes, 1970 (Folder 9)
  - Board representation, 1970 (Folder 10)
  - Board correspondence, 1971 (Folder 11)
  - General correspondence, 1971 December 3 (Folder 12)
  - Perroni Diary, 1970 November 16 (Folder 13)
  - Inventory, 1971 December 1 (Folder 14)
- RH MS Q274
  - Oversize articles on fair housing, 1958-1980 (Box Box 1)
- RH MS R232